I can't prescribe something that can be
harmful for an unvalidated reason.
>> What is an alarming hematocrit level is
under 52% safe 100%. And how to reduce
red blood cells?
>> Don't need to. There's no evidence you
should um if your red blood cells are
out of whack for a pathic reason, you
have to find the pathic cause of why
they're out of whack. And a lot of guys
that's going to be poor nutrition, sleep
apnnea, smoking, um other factors that
could probably go into it. Testosterone
alone, injectable especially can cause
elevated hematocrit. We see it. Um I
generally don't see it go I'd say the
highest was probably where I was at. I
was 57 58% hematocrit doing injections.
I stayed around 52% on cream. Um, when I
get concerned, it's not because of the
testosterone per se, but if I see a
guy's hemoglobin at 20 or 21 and their
hematocrit at 60 or above, I'm like, you
need to figure out what's going on with
your health. Like, you need to look into
some things. And usually you tease it
out and they do snore. They've never had
a sleep study. I'm like, you got to get
it. And a lot of them won't. They're
like, no, you know, I'll do it. And they
never do. Sleep apnea is a huge issue.
But again, a lot of this from being
overweight. A lot of people don't
they're not willing to admit that
they're at an unhealthy body fat. And
I'm not saying that's this guy's problem
at all. Um or everybody with elevated
hematocrit. I'm just saying though a lot
of people though don't realize with
sleep apnnea that a lot of it is from
body weight uh neck size things like
even muscular. It's not just fat. It's
just size in general. Like I've had to
come to grips with the fact that I feel
healthier and move better and sleep
better at 180 pounds instead of 220 and
18% body fat pretending like I'm big
when now I'm 180 175 at probably 10%.
But I feel better, you know, and I have
to get over this desire to just be this
mass monster because I'm never meant to
be that way. Okay. And the guys that are
who push the drugs to get that way or if
they're just naturally those bigger
guys, they need to look out for sleep
apnnea because it just can happen. And a
lot of it's uh not central. A lot of
it's with the obstructive with the
tongue. They can fix that lickety split
with a customized mouth guard that that
keeps the tongue and then you don't have
to worry about the CPAP and all the crap
that comes with that. So, um but as far
as yeah, the the alarming hematocrit no
first of all 54 I don't even blink twice
at that on somebody on TRT at all. again
the the top of the normal range used to
go up to 55% was normal uh when I got
into practice when I left residency and
then it changed a few years later so
it's like people are just becoming
chronically anemic so that's the new
normal right so that's the other thing I
want to tell people is statistics can't
give you an a prescription like you
can't get an ought from an is I cannot
look at a statistical norm and say well
I ought to be the inside that why how do
you know that that's just a description
what if everybody in that in that
distribution they're all disease right
like we don't know and whoever gets to
define health a healthy person in these
samples that's subjective. So, um you
got to take a lot of that stuff with a
grain of salt. That being said, if these
parameters are very much out of whack,
sometimes go look for a root cause. If
you can't find it and people feel fine
otherwise and they're okay with that
because I, you know, then that's all
that matters. I if they want to donate,
I'm like, listen, more power to you if
you want to go do that on your own. I'm
not writing a prescription for it
because I don't have any evidence that
it's necessary or good for you. Um, if
it makes them feel better from an
anxiety standpoint because the anxiety
is driving them crazy that's going to
affect their health negatively, then go
do it. You know, I get it. I just don't
want to be part of that because again, I
can't prescribe something that can be
harmful for an unvalidated reason
because we're not fixing anything by
just drawing off blood every now and
then when the blood may not be causing
the issue at all.
Hey,
hey, hey.